Wonder by RJ palaso driving IT WAS A long drive home.
I fell asleep in the back seat like I
always do, my head on Via’s lap like she was my pillow, a towel wrapped around the
seat belt so I wouldn’t drool all over her. Via fell asleep, too, and Mom and Dad
talk quietly about grownup things I don't care about.
I don’t know how long I was sleeping, but
when I woke up, there was a full moon outside the car window. It was a purple
night, and we were driving on a highway full of cars. And then I heard Mom and
Dad talking about me. “We can’t keep protecting him,” Mom whispered to Dad, who was driving. “We
can’t just pretend he’s going to wake up
tomorrow and this isn’t going to be his reality, because it is Nate, and we have
to help him learn to deal with it. We can’t just keep avoiding situations that
“So sending him off to middle school like a lamb to the slaughter Dad answered
angrily, but he didn’t even finish his sentence because he saw me in the mirror
looking up. “What’s a lamb to the slaughter?” I asked sleepily. “Go back to sleep, Auggie,” Dad
said softly. “Everyone will stare at me at school,” I said, suddenly crying. “Honey,” Mom
said. She turned around in the front seat and put her hand on my hand. “You know if
you don’t want to do this, you don’t have
to. But we spoke to the principal there and told him about you and he really
wants to meet you.” “What did you tell him about me?” “How funny you are, and how kind
and smart. When I told him you read Dragon Rider when you were six, he was
like, ‘Wow, I have to meet this kid.’” “Did you tell him anything else?” I said. Mom smiled
at me. Her smile kind of hugged me. “I told him all about your surgeries, and how
brave you are,” she said. “So he knows what I look like?” I asked. “Well, we brought
pictures from last summer in mon talk Dad said. “We showed him pictures of the
whole family. And that great shot of you holding that flounder on the boat!” “You
were there, too?” I have to admit I felt a little disappointed that he was part of
this. “We both talked to him, yes,” Dad said.
“He’s a really nice man.” “You would like him,” Mom added.
Suddenly it felt like they were on the same side. “Wait, so when did you meet him?”
I said. “He took us on a tour of the school last year,” said Mom. “Last year I
said. “So you’ve been thinking about this for a whole year and you didn’t tell me?”
“We didn’t know if you’d even get in, Auggie,” answered Mom. “It’s a very hard
school to get into. There’s a whole admissions process. I didn’t see the
point in telling you and having you get all worked up about it
unnecessarily.” “But you’re right, Auggie, we should have told you we found out last
month that you got in,” said Dad. “In hindsight,” sighed Mom, “yes, I
guess.” “Did that lady who came to the house that time have something to do
with this?” I said. “The one that gave me that test?” “Yes, actually,” said Mom, looking
guilty. “Yes.” “You told me it was an IQ test,”
I said. “I know, well, that was a white lie,”
she answered. “It was a test you needed to take to get into the school. You did very
well on it, by the way.” “So you lied,” I said.
“A white lie, but yes. Sorry,” she said, trying to smile, but when I didn’t smile
back, she turned around in her seat and faced forward. “What’s a lamb to the slaughter?” I
said. Mom sighed and gave dad a “look.” “I shouldn’t have said that,” Dad said,
looking at me in the rear view mirror is not true. Here’s the thing: Mommy and I
love you so much we want to protect you anyway we can. It’s just sometimes we
want to do it in different ways.” “I don’t want to go to school,” I
answered, folding my arms. “It would be good for you, Auggie,” said
Mom. “Maybe I’ll go next year,” I answered, looking out the window.
“This year would be better, Auggie,” said Mom. “You know why? Because you’ll be going
into fifth grade, and that’s the first year of middle school— —for everyone. You
won’t be the only new kid.” “I’ll be the only kid who looks like me,” I
said. “I’m not going to say it won’t be a
big challenge for you, because you know better than that,” she answered. “But it’ll
be good for you, Auggie. You’ll make lots of friends. And you’ll learn things you
never learn with me.” She turned in her seat again and looked at me. “When we took
the tour, you know what they had in their science lab? A little baby chick that was
just hatching out of its egg. It was so cute! Auggie, it actually kind of reminded
me of you when you were a little baby with those big brown eyes of yours. I
usually love when they talk about when I was a
baby. Sometimes I want to curl up into a little tiny ball and let them hug me and
kiss me all over. I miss being a baby, not
knowing stuff. But I wasn’t in the mood
for that now. “I don’t want to go,” I said. “How about this? Can you at least
meet Mr. Tushman before making up your mind?” Mom asked. “Mr tush man I said. “He’s
the principal,” answered Mom. “Mr tushman I repeated. “I know, right?” Dad answered,
smiling and looking at me in the rearview mirror. “Can you believe that
name, Auggie? I mean, who on earth would ever agree to have a name like Mr tush
man I smiled even though I didn’t want
to let them see me smile. Dad was the one
person in in the world who could make me laugh no matter how much I didn’t want
to laugh. Dad always made everyone laugh.
“Auggie, you know, you should go to that school just so you can hear his name
said over the loudspeaker!” Dad said excitedly. “Can you imagine how funny that
would be? Hello, hello piging Mr tush man He was using a fake high old lady voice.
“Hi, Mr tush man I see you’re running a little behind today! Did your car get
rear ended again? What a bum wrap I started laughing, not even because
I thought he was being that funny but because I wasn’t in the mood to stay mad
anymore. “It could be worse, though!” Dad continued in his normal voice. “Mommy and
I had a professor in college called Miss Butt.” Mom was laughing now, too. “Is that
for real?” I said.
“Roberta Butt,” Mom answered, raising her hand as if to swear bobby Butt.” “She had
huge cheeks,” said Dad. “Nate!” said Mom. “What?
She had big cheeks as all I’m saying.” Mom laughed and shook her head at the same
time. “Hey hey, I know!” said Dad excitedly.
“Let’s fix them up on a blind date! Can you imagine? Miss Butt, meet Mr. Tushman. Mr.
Tushman, here’s Miss Butt. They could get married and have a bunch of little
Tushies.” “Poor Mr tush man answered Mom, shaking her head. “Auggie hasn’t even met the man yet,
Nate!” “Who’s Mr.
Tushman FIA said groggy She had just woken up. “He’s the principal of my new school,” I
answered paging Mr tushman I WOULD HAVE been more nervous
about meeting Mr. Tushman if IID known I was also going to be meeting some kids
from the new school. But I didn’t know, so if anything, I was kind of giggly. I
couldn’t stop thinking about all the jokes Daddy had made about Mr. Tushman’s
name. So when me and Mom arrived at Beacher Prep a few weeks before the
start of school, and I saw Mr. Tushman standing there, waiting for us at the entrance,
I started giggling right away. He didn’t look at all like what I pictured, though.
I guess I thought he would have a huge
butt, but he didn’t. In fact, he was a pretty normal guy. Tall and thin. Old but
not really old. He seemed nice. He shook my mom’s hand
first. “Hi, Mr. Tushman, it’s so nice to see
you again,” said Mom. “This is my son, August.” Mr. Tushman looked right at me and smiled
and nodded. He put his hand out for me to shake. “Hi, August,” he said, totally normally.
“It’s a pleasure to meet you.” “Hi,” I mumbled, dropping my hand into his hand while I
looked down at his feet. He was wearing red Adidas. “So,” he said, kneeling down in front
of me so I couldn’t look at his sneakers
but had to look at his face, “your mom and dad have told me a lot about
you.” “Like what have they told you?” I asked. “Sorry?” “Honey, you have to speak up,” said
Mom. “Like what?” I asked, trying not to mumble. I admit I have a bad habit of
mumbling. “Well, that you like to read,” said Mr. Tushman, “and that you’re a great
artist.” He had blue eyes with white eyelashes.
“And you’re into science, right uhhuh I said, nodding. “We have a
couple of great science electives at beer he said. “Maybe you’ll take one of
them uhhuh I said, though I had no idea what an elective was. “So, are you ready to
take a tour?” “You mean we’re doing that now?” I
said. “Did you think we were going to the movies?” he answered, smiling as he stood
up. “You didn’t tell me we were taking a tour,” I said to Mom in my accusing
voice. “Auggie she started to say. “It’ll be fine, August,” said Mr. Tushman, holding his
hand out to me. “I promise.” I think he wanted me to take his
hand, but I took Mom’s instead. He smiled and started walking toward the end
entrance. Mommy gave my hand a little squeeze, though I don’t know if it was an
“I love you” squeeze or an “I’m sorry” squeeze. Probably a little of both. The
only school I’d ever been inside before was Vias when I went with Mom and Dad to
watch Via sing in spring concerts and stuff like that. This school was very
different. It was smaller. It smelled like a hospital nice Mrs
Garcia WE FOLLOWED MR. TUSHMAN down a few hallways. There weren’t a lot of people
around. And the few people who were there didn’t seem to notice me at all, though
that may have been because they didn’t see me. I sort of hid behind Mom as I
walked. I know that sounds kind of babyish of me, but I wasn’t feeling very
brave right then. We ended up in a small room with the words OFFICE OF THE MIDDLE
SCHOOL DIRECTOR on the door. Inside, there was a desk with a nice seeming lady sitting behind
it. “This is Mrs. Garcia,” said Mr. Tushman, and the lady smiled at Mom and took off
her glasses and got up out of her chair.
My mother shook her hand and said Isabella Pullman, nice to meet you.” “And
this is August,” Mr. Tushman said. Mom kind of stepped to the side a bit, so I would
move forward. Then that thing happened that I’ve seen happen a million times
before. When I looked up at her, Mrs.
Garcia’s eyes dropped for a second. It was so fast no one else would have
noticed, since the rest of her face stayed exactly the same. She was smiling a really shiny
smile. “Such a pleasure to meet you, August,” she said, holding out her hand for me to shake.
“Hi,” I said quietly, giving her my hand, but
I didn’t want to look at her face, so I kept staring at her glasses, which hung
from a chain around her neck. “Wow, what a firm grip!” said Mrs.
Garcia. Her hand was really warm. “The kids got to kill her handshake,” Mr. Tushman
agreed, and everyone laughed above my head. “You can call me Mrs. G,”
Mrs. Garcia said. I think she was talking to me, but I was looking at all the stuff
on her desk now. “That’s what everyone calls me. Mrs. G, I forgot my combination.
Mrs. G, I need a late pass. Mrs. G, I want to change my
elective.” “Mrs G is actually the one who runs the place,” said Mr. Tushman, which
again made all the grown-ups laugh. “I’m here every morning by 7:30 Mrs. Garcia
continued, still looking at me while I stared at her brown sandals with small
purple flowers on the buckles. “So if you ever need anything, August, I’m the one to
ask. And you can ask me anything.” “Okay,” I mumbled. “Oh, look at that cute baby,” Mom
said, pointing to one of the photographs on Mrs. Garcia’s bulletin board. “Is he
yours?” “No, my goodness!” said Mrs. Garcia, smiling a big smile now that was totally
different from her shiny smile. “You’ve just made my day. He’s my
grandson.” “What a cuttie said Mom, shaking her head. “How old?” “In that first picture
he was five months, I think he’s big now.
Almost 8 years old!” “Wow,” said Mom Mom, nodding and smiling.
“Well, he is absolutely beautiful.” “Thank you!” said Mrs. Garcia,
nodding like she was about to say something else about her grandson. But
then all of a sudden her smile got a little smaller. “We’re all going to take very
good care of August,” she said to Mom, and I saw her give Mom’s hand a little
squeeze. I looked at Mom’s face, and that’s when I realized she was just as
nervous as I was. I guess I liked Mrs.
Garcia— —when she wasn’t wearing her shiny
[Music]
smile